The man known to history as George Washington
was born on the 22nd of February 1732 at his
father’s plantation of Pope’s Creek in
Westmoreland County in the Colony of Virginia,
one of the thirteen British colonies in North
America.
His father was Augustine Washington, a member
of Virginia’s landed gentry, and a successful
businessman who owned several tobacco plantations
as well as iron operations in Virginia and
neighbouring Maryland in partnership with
the English Principio Company.
He was also active in the local militia and
was a justice of the peace and sheriff for
Westmoreland County.
Augustine had married his first wife Jane
Butler in 1715, who bore him four children
before her death in 1729.
A couple of years later in 1731 he would marry
the 23-year-old Mary Johnson Ball, who would
give him a further six children, of whom George
was the eldest.
Mary Washington was born in 1708 to an elderly
father who died three years later, leaving
her 400 acres of land, while her mother died
when she was twelve.
The orphaned Mary was left in the care of
family friend George Eskridge, who was probably
responsible for introducing her to Augustine
Washington.
Thus, when Mary gave birth to her first son,
she named him George.
Brought up as a loyal subject of the British
Empire, as a child George Washington could
never imagine that one day he would be responsible
for leading the successful military rebellion
to break free from Britain and establish the
United States of America.
He grew up in eastern Virginia amidst a vast
expanse of farmland with plantation houses
and small towns dotted across the landscape.
Within the British social hierarchy, the Washingtons
were considered commoners, far removed from
the regal splendour of the court of King George
II.
Nevertheless, within the American colonies
the Washingtons were by no means poor, and
with over 10,000 acres of plantation land
together with his other commercial interests,
Augustine Washington was certainly a member
of the local elite.
His wealth and prosperity depended in part
on slave labour, allowing plantation owners
a lot of free time, which was typically filled
with fox hunts, horse races, and other entertainments.
Augustine Washington’s tendency to move
around his properties to better manage his
business interests meant that George had an
unsettled childhood.
In 1735 the family moved to the 2500-acre
estate of Little Hunting Creek on the banks
of the Potomac River, and three years later
in 1738 they moved once again to Ferry Farm
on the Rappahannock River across from the
port of Fredericksburg, and a short ride away
from the ironworks at Accokeek Creek.
From his house, George could see the ships
being loaded with tobacco, iron, and other
commodities which would soon fuel the very
early stages of the Industrial Revolution
and in return, the colony of Virginia grew
steadily richer.
One of the most important figures in George’s
childhood was his half-brother, Lawrence.
Fourteen years older than George, Lawrence
studied at Appleby Grammar School where he
stayed on as a teacher until the age of twenty.
It was around this time, when George was six
years old, that the two brothers first met.
He heard stories of Lawrence’s service as
a captain in a Virginia company in 1739 during
the War of Jenkin’s Ear against Spain, named
after the British naval captain whose ear
had been cut off during an altercation with
the Spanish several years earlier.
Lawrence was part of an expeditionary force
led by Admiral Edward Vernon which attacked
the Spanish port of Cartagena in South America.
The effort proved a bloody failure as the
force was cut down by the enemy and yellow
fever.
Captain Washington never made it off the ship,
blaming General Thomas Wentworth, who treated
the American soldiers with disdain and did
not even let them leave their ships.
In spite of this, Lawrence Washington proudly
served the British army as a commissioned
officer and was appointed adjutant general
of Virginia, with responsibility over the
organisation of the colony’s militia companies.
When his father transferred him to the management
of the estate at Little Hunting Creek, he
renamed it Mount Vernon after the admiral.
George may have expected to receive the same
classical education as his elder half-brothers,
but such hopes were extinguished on the 12th
of April 1743, when his father died at the
age of 49.
The 11-year-old George’s share of his father’s
inheritance was Ferry Farm, but his mother
Mary continued to run the estate and would
continue to do so as George reached adulthood.
Mary’s strict upbringing of her five surviving
children meant that the relationship between
mother and son was cool and distant, with
George addressing her in formal terms in his
letters as “Honoured Madam.”
He looked forward to his trips to visit Lawrence
at Mount Vernon as an escape from his overbearing
mother.
Details of George Washington’s early education
are sketchy and any instruction he received
was likely rather basic.
The available evidence suggests that he had
lessons in basic mathematics and picked up
knowledge of business and economics of his
own accord.
As a teenager he would read widely in history
and philosophy as well as the popular fiction
of the time.
He also enjoyed physical activity and outdoor
pursuits, swimming in the Rappahannock, and
proved to be an excellent horseback rider,
an attribute that would serve him well in
his military career.
Later in life Washington regretted not having
the opportunity to study French, Latin, and
Greek, the signs of social and intellectual
distinction of the day.
Among his better educated friends and colleagues
such as John Adams, Thomas Jefferson, and
Alexander Hamilton, who provided the theoretical
and intellectual foundations of the United
States of America, Washington’s intellect
seemed backward and provincial.
In his own terms, however, he was an intelligent
man who could translate ideas into action.
After losing his father, Washington came to
rely even more heavily on his brother Lawrence,
who had not only been elected to the House
of Burgesses but had married Ann Fairfax,
whose family owned more than five million
acres, managed by her father Colonel William
Fairfax on behalf of his English cousin, the
6th Baron Fairfax.
The young George Washington befriended Ann’s
brother George William Fairfax who was eight
years his senior, and also won the affection
of her father the colonel.
In 1746 the elder Fairfax and Lawrence planned
to help George escape the clutches of his
mother by joining the Royal Navy.
Unwilling to lose a useful helping hand on
the farm, Mary eventually vetoed the plan.
Thwarted in his ambitions to go to sea, at
the age of 15 George decided to become a surveyor,
a lucrative profession as settlers continued
to expand westwards.
This training allowed him to appreciate geographical
features on maps and in the real world, a
skill which he would use throughout his professional
life.
His first job in the spring of 1748 was to
help the Fairfaxes divide up their vast domains
into plots for further development.
Within a couple of years he would make his
first investments in land, buying up over
2,000 acres by the time he turned twenty.
George would add to his land holdings in 1752
following the death of Lawrence from tuberculosis
that July at the age of 34, leaving behind
his wife and a baby daughter.
Lawrence stipulated that in the event of their
deaths, his estate of Mount Vernon would pass
on to George.
The death of his brother dealt a heavy blow
to George, who had hoped to emulate Lawrence’s
military career.
After lobbying the Lieutenant Governor of
Virginia Robert Dinwiddie, he was appointed
adjutant general of his home district in February
1753 with the rank of major.
Major Washington would soon be a very busy
man.
By 1753, both the British and French empires
owned large tracts of land in North America.
The thirteen British colonies stretched along
the eastern coast, bounded by the Allegheny
Mountains to the west, while the French territories
ran from New Orleans in the southwest through
the Mississippi to the Great Lakes and the
Saint Lawrence River in the North.
As both empires expanded their footprint,
they soon had competing claims on the vast
Ohio Country.
In 1752, the French began building several
forts in the disputed territory, and the following
year Lieutenant Governor Dinwiddie, a leading
investor in the Ohio Company, received permission
from London to build a set of British forts
alongside instructions to inform the French
to leave the area.
The 21-year-old Washington was chosen for
this special mission and set off with a small
company and crossed the Alleghenies in November
1753.
Washington executed his task diligently, not
only carrying out his diplomatic duties but
gathering intelligence on the terrain and
the strength of the French and Native American
presence in the area.
Upon his return to the colonial capital of
Williamsburg in January 1754, his journal
was adapted into a report for the council
and was passed onto London, where it informed
British military preparations to defend the
Ohio Country against the French.
Washington secured for himself a major role
in these military preparations, leading a
small militia force who would march to the
Forks of the Ohio River and construct a fort.
At the same time, he was promoted to the rank
of lieutenant colonel, though he was disappointed
that as a colonial officer his salary was
much lower than those of regular officers
in the British army who had royal commissions.
In early April, Washington set out with 160
men into the wilderness, only to learn that
a force of 1,000 Frenchmen had captured the
fort the British were building at the Forks
and renamed it Fort Duquesne after the Governor
General of French Canada.
Washington and his Native American allies
called for reinforcements and made camp.
On the 28th of May 1754, Washington and his
company found a small group of French soldiers
encamped in a secluded position.
Believing them to be up to no good, Washington’s
men surrounded them and a quick firefight
resulted in a French surrender.
During the skirmish a French officer delivering
a diplomatic message asking the British to
evacuate the Ohio County was supposedly brutally
killed by one of Washington’s Native American
allies.
The act sparked an international incident
and while Washington was applauded in the
colonies for being a hero, the authorities
in London considered his behaviour reckless
and further evidence that colonial soldiers
could not be trusted.
Anticipating a French response, Washington
hastily constructed a wooden fort named Fort
Necessity.
During these preparations his commanding officer
had died after falling off his horse, and
Washington took command of the Virginia Regiment
as colonel.
When he disregarded his Native American allies’
advice to withdraw on account of the inadequate
defences provided by the fort, they deserted
him and left the British to fight alone.
When the French and their Native American
allies attacked on the 3rd of July, Washington
put up a brave fight but lost a third of his
men and was forced to surrender.
It was a humiliating defeat and he had made
many mistakes owing to his lack of experience,
but he learned from it the effectiveness of
the enemy’s mobile tactics and the futility
of defending poor positions.
The defeat could have ended Washington’s
military career before it started, but instead
after a few weeks had passed, he and his men
were praised for their brave last stand against
the odds.
While the Virginia Regiment was disbanded,
leaving Washington without a command, his
personal fortunes improved when his late brother
Lawrence’s daughter died at the end of December.
As Ann had already remarried, Washington agreed
to lease the estate of Mount Vernon from his
sister-in-law, and made it his main residence.
Not long after he moved into Mount Vernon,
Washington received news in February 1755
that General Edward Braddock had landed with
two regiments of reinforcements from Britain.
Washington rushed to offer his services and
Braddock was happy to have him as aide-de-camp.
Leaving his younger brother Jack in charge
of Mount Vernon, Washington joined Braddock
in June and the army made its slow progress
towards Fort Duquesne.
Although personally warm towards Washington,
Braddock held the same disdain for colonial
soldiers as many of his fellow officers in
the regular army, and refused to heed his
aide-de-camp’s advice to travel lightly,
before eventually giving in to the situation
to pick up the glacial pace of the advance.
On the 9th of July Braddock approached Fort
Duquesne with more than two thousand men and
divided his army into three columns to attack.
The British were surprised by the ferocious
defence of 900 French and Native Americans
whose tactics once again proved superior.
Washington bravely carried out Braddock’s
orders to rally the troops, exposing himself
to great danger with two horses shot from
underneath him.
This was not enough to bring victory, and
Braddock himself was mortally wounded.
Following Braddock’s death, the Virginia
Regiment was reformed and Washington was appointed
commander of all of Virginia’s forces.
Despite these rapid promotions, Washington
remained unhappy about not receiving a royal
commission.
He resented London’s strategy to pursue
active operations in Canada while remaining
on the defensive on the frontiers of Virginia,
leaving him nothing to do but to train and
drill his men.
He was dismayed by the state of the militiamen
under his responsibility, many of whom deserted
en masse.
In late 1757, he was struck down by a grave
illness that prompted him to return to Mount
Vernon.
During this time he would begin to make changes
to the estate and create a house fit for an
English country gentleman.
In early 1758, after a brief courtship, he
was engaged to Martha Dandridge Custis, a
wealthy 26-year-old widow whose husband had
died the previous summer leaving her with
two young children.
A warm and sociable woman, Martha was the
polar opposite of her mother-in-law Mary,
and proved a steadfast support in her husband’s
life and career, capable not only of carrying
out the domestic duties of a housewife but
also of running the Mount Vernon estate in
her husband’s absence.
In July 1758 Washington returned to action
as the British made a further attempt to seize
Fort Duquesne and avenge the loss of Braddock,
this time serving under the Scottish General
John Forbes.
In the meantime, he entered political office
for the first time by handsomely winning election
to the Virginia House of Burgesses representing
Frederick County, a reflection of his reputation
as a war hero.
Despite some disagreements with his superior
and a devastating friendly fire incident which
claimed the lives of more than twenty of his
men, Washington led 2,500 men and successfully
recaptured Fort Duquesne in November 1758.
Instead of the ferocious defence he had met
on previous occasions, he encountered no resistance
at all, as the French chose to abandon and
destroy the fort after falling out with their
Native American allies.
The British rebuilt it and named it Fort Pitt,
after war minister William Pitt, while the
city that was built around it would take the
name of Pittsburgh, in the state of Pennsylvania.
The action would be Washington’s last in
the French and Indian War, better known as
the Seven Years War in Europe, where the fighting
between Britain and France, supported by their
respective allies, would last until 1763.
Washington returned to Mount Vernon, and married
Martha on the 6th of January 1759, making
him one of Virginia’s richest landowners.
In their efforts to emulate the upper class
in England, importing the latest fashions
from London, Washington became increasingly
indebted to his London agents and resented
their power over the colonial planters.
At the same time he carried out his civic
duties in the House of Burgesses, serving
on committees related to military matters
and limiting any speeches to the most important
points of the debate.
For the next two decades of his life, Washington
would devote his energies to his plantation,
in particular to growing tobacco.
This proved a poor economic decision, and
one Washington would later regret, as the
quality of the tobacco crop was highly dependent
on weather conditions, while international
market prices were volatile.
These factors contributed to Washington’s
struggles repaying his debts to his creditors
in London.
Another key aspect of tobacco farming was
its labour intensiveness and dependence on
slavery.
During his life, Washington owned over 600
slaves.
He and his fellow planters treated slaves
as any other type of property to be bought
and sold, although over time he grew to despise
the practice and treated his slaves more humanely
than most of his peers, looking after their
health and eventually refusing to sell any
of his slaves in order to keep families together.
The French and Indian War ended in 1763 in
a decisive victory for the British in North
America.
France had lost Canada to Britain and Louisiana
to Spain.
The cost to the British Treasury had been
enormous, and half the national budget went
on interest repayments on government debt.
In an effort to fill the hole in government
coffers, Parliament attempted to impose taxes
and other economic costs onto the North American
colonies, preventing the existing colonies
from further westward expansion.
As a soldier, Washington had resented the
superior attitude of the British authorities
and their refusal to give him a royal commission.
As a businessman, Washington now had cause
to consider the decisions of the British authorities
to be detrimental to his economic interests.
The most infamous piece of legislation passed
by Parliament was the Stamp Act of 1765, which
imposed a tax on all printed material, including
legal documents, newspapers, and playing cards.
Washington may not have been the most radical
of the voices protesting against the Stamp
Act on the political stage, but he considered
the tax unconstitutional and wrote to his
representatives in London that the colonies
would begin to boycott British goods in favour
of domestic substitutes, and courts would
shut down, preventing British creditors from
collecting their dues from their American
debtors.
At around the same time and perhaps concerned
about his dependency on British credit, Washington
decided to diversify away from tobacco, eventually
abandoning the crop altogether in favour of
wheat, corn, hemp, and dozens of other crops.
Mount Vernon also had an extensive fishing
enterprise from the plentiful stocks on the
Potomac, initially for consumption within
the house and later salted and cured for export
to international markets.
The diversification away from the labour-intensive
tobacco crop encouraged Washington to train
his surplus slaves in a number of crafts such
as carpentry, bricklaying, smithing, and baking.
Although Parliament repealed the Stamp Act
in 1766, it continued to assert the right
to taxation in the colonies, prompting sustained
opposition which spread throughout the Thirteen
Colonies.
In 1767 the Townshend Acts, named after the
British Chancellor of the Exchequer at the
time, levied duties on paint, lead, glass,
paper, and tea.
During the winter of 1768-69, Washington’s
attitude became more radical and he supported
a boycott of British goods.
While he did not rule out armed insurrection
against what he considered a sustained attack
on American liberties, he believed that non-violent
economic measures should be used first.
In April 1769 Washington took a more proactive
role in the House of Burgesses intending to
present a plan for the importation of British
goods developed alongside his friend George
Mason of Fairfax County.
The following month the assembly voted in
favour of a set of resolves which asserted
that the House of Burgesses had the sole right
to tax Virginians.
In response the royal governor, Lord Botecourt,
dissolved the body, forcing the burgesses
to reconvene in a tavern, where they debated
and adopted Washington’s proposals to boycott
the goods subject to taxation under the Townshend
Acts.
The move had some effect, prompting the new
British government under Lord North to repeal
the Townshend Acts, keeping only the levies
on tea to continue asserting Parliament’s
right to taxation.
The situation had temporarily been diffused,
but the remaining taxes on tea provoked the
Boston Tea Party on the 16th of December 1773,
when a group of men from the American patriot
organisation Sons of Liberty boarded a merchant
ship belonging to the East India Company and
dumped its valuable cargo of tea into Boston
Harbour.
While Washington was dismayed by the protest,
he was furious at the British response, which
involved passing a number of draconian measures
against Boston collectively known as the Intolerable
Acts, the most important of which closed the
port of Boston to trade until the East India
Company was compensated for the loss of cargo.
In the House of Burgesses, Washington supported
an initiative to show solidarity with Boston
by convening a congress of all thirteen colonies
to protect their collective rights.
In July 1774, while chairing a meeting in
Fairfax County, which he had represented since
1765, Washington passed the Fairfax Resolves
which he had drafted alongside George Mason,
asserting that “taxation and representation
are in their nature inseparable.”
Washington thus became one of the leading
advocates of resistance against Britain, and
on the 5th of August he was elected to Virginia’s
seven-man delegation to the First Continental
Congress in Philadelphia, which would meet
the following month.
Surrounded by some of the finest orators of
the day, Washington spoke rarely but effectively,
bringing together different viewpoints.
As the delegates were increasingly convinced
that war would break out, Washington’s name
was on many of their lips when it came to
a commander-in-chief.
The 42-year-old Washington had developed a
sense of political maturity that had been
absent in his younger days, and did not actively
lobby for the command, confident that his
reputation would be enough to secure the post.
For the time being, the Continental Congress
was content to set up a Continental Association
to coordinate efforts among the colonies to
ban trade with Great Britain.
On the 19th of April 1775, British redcoats
and American militiamen exchanged fire at
Concord and Lexington in Massachusetts, marking
the outbreak of the American Revolutionary
War.
Washington had already secured election to
the Second Continental Congress, which opened
on the 10th of May, with the agenda firmly
focused on raising militia and volunteers
across the colonies.
Washington appeared in the Congress wearing
his colonel’s uniform and his expertise
in military affairs was in high demand among
his fellow delegates.
On the 14th of June, the Congress assumed
control of the volunteer army laying siege
to the British forces in Boston under the
command of General Thomas Gage, thereby creating
the Continental Army, and Washington was appointed
“General and Commander in Chief of the army
of the United Colonies” on the 16th.
While on his way to take command of the Continentals
in Boston, Washington received news of the
Battle of Bunker Hill on the 17th of June,
where 2,000 men under General William Howe
successfully captured the American positions,
but at the cost of 1,000 casualties, demonstrating
that the Continentals were more than capable
of putting up a fight.
Upon arriving in Boston, Washington sought
to instil in his men the idea that they were
a national army, rather than from a collection
of states.
Upon inspecting his army, he was disappointed
to find that he only had 14,000 men fit for
duty living in poor conditions, while supplies
of gunpowder were dangerously low.
Fearing British spies, he kept quiet about
these deficiencies to all but his closest
confidantes.
During this period the commander-in-chief
came to be particularly close to Brigadier
General Nathaniel Greene from Rhode Island,
as well as 25-year-old artillery commander
Colonel Henry Knox, a Boston bookseller who
had learned everything about military affairs
from the books and the British officers he
talked to in his shop.
Washington struggled in his efforts to create
a professional standing army.
Recruits were authorised to serve for one
year, with the effect that no sooner had they
been trained and drilled to fight effectively,
they would melt away and return to their homes.
As he faced losing his entire army on the
1st of January 1776, Washington attempted
to persuade the men to reenlist, but fewer
than 10,000 would agree to do so by the end
of the year.
In order to bolster numbers, Washington considered
recruiting from the black population.
While black soldiers had fought in the ranks
of the volunteers in Massachusetts and were
considered every bit as brave as their white
counterparts, as a leading figure of Virginia’s
slaveholding class the thought of arming black
men raised the prospect of slave rebellion.
At a war council in October Washington prohibited
any black soldiers from serving in the Continental
Army, but upon hearing that Virginia’s Governor
Lord Dunmore had promised to free slaves who
were to join the British army, Washington
compromised and allowed free blacks to serve
in his ranks, who would make up around 10%
of the Continental Army.
As winter approached, Washington realised
he could not abandon his army and return to
Mount Vernon, and instead invited his wife
Martha to stay with him.
Martha Washington would spend half the war
with her husband on campaign, serving as a
trusted confidante for his concerns and anxieties
about his army and the war.
The condition Washington’s men found themselves
in during the first winter of the war caused
morale to plummet, leading the men to question
if their cause could ever succeed.
The politicians in Philadelphia were still
split on whether to declare independence,
and some still believed in petitioning King
George III and reconciling with Britain.
The publication of Thomas Paine’s pamphlet
Common Sense in January 1776 highlighted the
tyrannical power of monarchy and galvanised
the movement for independence.
Spirits further increased on the 17th of January,
when Henry Knox arrived after accomplishing
the incredible logistical feat of hauling
almost sixty pieces of cannon from Fort Ticonderoga
in New York near the Canadian border across
the December snows to Washington’s camp.
Although Washington still lacked the powder
for a full assault on Boston, he successfully
manoeuvred the cannon onto the Dorchester
Heights overlooking the city during the course
of a single night on the 4th of March, leaving
the British with no choice but to evacuate.
Having captured Boston without losing a single
man, Washington hurried to New York, believing
that General Howe would attempt to take the
city.
Although the city’s geography made it difficult
to defend from the British army, and there
was a large population of Loyalists sympathising
with the British, Washington recognised the
political and commercial importance to the
Continental cause and felt compelled to make
a stand despite being significantly outnumbered.
Meanwhile, the drumbeat for independence was
sounding ever louder and the Declaration of
Independence drafted by Thomas Jefferson,
Washington’s colleague in the Virginia House
of Burgesses, was adopted by Congress on the
4th of July 1776 and was received with wild
enthusiasm by the Continental army when Washington
read the declaration to them on the 8th.
The enthusiasm was premature, as the British
army and navy, commanded by brothers William
and Richard Howe, soon descended on New York
at the head of 32,000 men and seventy warships,
keen to defeat the rebellion once and for
all.
By mid-August Washington had 23,000 men under
his command, but most were inexperienced recruits.
Meanwhile, when the British landed two thirds
of their force at Long Island, Washington
misread it as a diversion and only sent 6,000
men to defend the Brooklyn Heights to the
west of the island, keeping most of his men
in Manhattan.
On the 26th the Continentals were surrounded
by the British, with 300 killed and 1,000
captured, but on the night of the 29th of
August Washington took advantage of Howe’s
reluctance to stage a full pursuit by evacuating
all the men from Long Island to Manhattan.
The commander himself was on the last boat
across the East River, shrouded from the British
by thick fog.
A few days later, Washington withdrew from
the city to the north.
The Continentals had built Fort Washington
and Fort Lee overlooking the Hudson River
but these were taken by the British in November,
forcing the Continentals to flee across to
New Jersey.
These setbacks also called into question Washington’s
command abilities, and his subordinate General
Charles Lee schemed to replace him.
Upon discovering the plot Washington said
nothing to Lee, who received his comeuppance
in mid-December when he was captured by the
British.
Washington’s Continental Army was a bedraggled
group of fewer than 4,000 men when it crossed
the Delaware River to Pennsylvania, while
Howe’s army was in striking range of Philadelphia,
forcing the Continental Congress to evacuate
to Baltimore.
With little to lose and with a few thousand
extra reinforcements under General Horatio
Gates, Washington planned a daring operation
back across the Delaware to surprise three
regiments of Hessian mercenaries stationed
in Trenton, New Jersey.
Washington planned to cross the river on the
night of Christmas Day in order to surprise
the enemy, whom he expected to be drunk at
the time.
Despite a fierce snowstorm which meant his
main column of 2,400 men only got to the other
side of the river by four in the morning on
the 26th, Washington pressed on to Trenton.
Although the Hessians were sober, they failed
to believe that Washington would attempt such
a daring operation in such foul weather.
The element of surprise and the effectiveness
of Henry Knox’s artillery, combined with
Washington’s effective use of terrain to
beat back a counterattack, obliged the Hessians
to surrender.
The Continentals killed and wounded 100 Hessians
and captured 900 more, all for the loss of
fewer than 10 men.
While Washington is usually considered a defensive
general who avoided battle with the odds against
him, he was capable of some of the most daring
attacks in the history of warfare.
The success at Trenton was followed up by
a similarly lopsided victory at Princeton
a few days later, enabling Washington’s
men to push forward and expel the British
almost completely from New Jersey.
The victories provided a boost to morale and
allowed Congress to move back to Philadelphia,
but with only a few thousand men Washington
was obliged to remain on the defensive, launching
frequent raids into enemy territory.
In March 1777 the 22-year-old artillery captain
Alexander Hamilton joined Washington’s staff
as aide-de-camp.
The talented Hamilton was able to handle much
of the commander-in-chief’s correspondence
and would later become his chief aide.
At the end of July Washington welcomed to
his side the Marquis de Lafayette, a 20-year-old
French aristocrat who shared in the political
ideals of the American Revolution and defied
a royal order to travel to America and volunteer
his service to the cause.
With Lafayette at his side, Washington and
Congress hoped that France would be persuaded
to join an alliance with the nascent United
States.
During the first half of 1777, Washington
remained on the defensive and awaited Howe’s
movements.
By the end of August, the British commander
landed on the Chesapeake Bay and marched on
Philadelphia.
Keen not to lose the capital without a fight,
Washington hurried to cut him off and deployed
his army amongst the ravines of Brandywine
Creek on the southwestern approaches of the
city, anticipating a decisive battle.
On the 11th of September, Howe launched his
attack, sending 5,000 Hessians to attack Washington’s
main defensive position in a frontal assault,
while he led a force of more than 8,000 men
on a long flanking manoeuvre, aiming to cross
the Brandywine at a couple of undefended fords.
While the Continentals held firm against the
frontal assault, by midday Washington wondered
about the whereabouts of the main enemy force,
and soon began to receive reports of an enemy
flanking manoeuvre.
The American commander realised that he had
been outwitted and galloped to the sector
in question to find two brigades of redcoats,
not realising that Howe’s entire force was
on its way.
By four in the afternoon, three columns of
British troops were thrown into the attack,
routing the Continentals.
At the end of the battle the Continentals
sustained more than 1,000 casualties, including
400 captured, while British casualties were
half the number.
The defeat at Brandywine resulted in the British
occupation of Philadelphia, forcing Congress
to evacuate again, this time to Trenton.
Although the Continentals had fought bravely
at Brandywine, once again Washington’s failure
to prepare adequately and his inability to
respond quickly when the battle did not unfold
as planned resulted in catastrophe for the
American cause.
The American commander was not disheartened,
and on the 3rd of October less than a month
after Brandywine, Washington planned a daring
night attack on Howe’s camp at Germantown,
hoping to repeat his heroics at Trenton the
previous winter.
However, this time round Washington’s plans
unravelled in the middle of the night and
he was forced to abandon the attack after
sustaining twice as many casualties as the
British once again.
He tried his best to make light of the defeat
in reports to Congress, and his audacious
attack demonstrated to the British that there
was still a lot of fight left in the battered
and bruised Continental Army.
While Washington’s main army had suffered
a series of setbacks against General Howe,
on the 17th of October General Horatio Gates
had defeated and captured a British army of
5,000 men under General John Burgoyne at Saratoga
in New York, which had been attempting to
march south to join Howe.
While Washington welcomed the news of Gates’
stunning victory, he felt threatened by a
subordinate who had previously been a critic,
and whom he believed was seeking the supreme
command for himself.
These fears were confirmed when Gates was
named as the President of the Congressional
Board of War, giving him supervisory powers
over Washington and his army.
The Board of War also appointed General Thomas
Conway as inspector general, with extensive
powers over training and discipline which
bypassed Washington, promoting him to major
general in the process.
When Conway arrived at Washington’s camp
at Valley Forge to announce his appointment,
the commander was incensed and informed Conway
that his generals would not recognise his
authority, obliging Congress to send Conway
elsewhere.
Washington had stood firm, retained his command,
and increased his authority.
Washington’s quarters for the winter of
1777-78 at Valley Forge, twenty miles to the
northwest of Philadelphia, has entered into
American legend.
For yet another winter the Continental Army
was in a desperate state and risked falling
apart, with thousands of men sick, hungry,
cold, and demoralised.
Washington’s efforts to beg Congress for
supplies came to nothing, and he came to realise
that the existing constitution, the Articles
of Confederation, which left most political
power with individual states, gave Congress
little power and undermined his efforts to
create a national army.
Yet Washington’s presence at the camp helped
to keep his men together in these trying times
when other armies may have melted away, while
Martha Washington’s care and attention for
the men won her respect and affection throughout
the ranks.
Washington was also helped by the arrival
of Friedrich von Steuben, a Prussian officer
who had served in Frederick the Great’s
armies during the Seven Years War.
The Prussian army was considered the best
in Europe, famous for its discipline and order,
attributes which the Continentals sorely lacked.
Within a matter of weeks, Steuben drilled
the army in line and column formations and
associated manoeuvres, and also began working
on a drill manual which would remain in use
by the United States army for almost a century.
By the beginning of March, Washington had
12,000 men at his disposal ready for action.
A far more significant boost to the American
war effort came in the form of an alliance
with France, signed in Paris on the 6th of
February 1778.
The alliance changed the strategic picture
of the war, forcing the British troops under
their new commander Sir Henry Clinton, to
withdraw from Philadelphia to New York and
detach 8,000 men to defend the West Indies
from the French.
While Clinton’s men were on the retreat,
Washington ordered General Charles Lee, recently
released in a prisoner exchange to take up
his previous role as second-in-command, to
lead a vanguard of 5,000 men against the British
at Monmouth Court House.
Lee, who had advised against the operation,
launched a half-hearted attack that was easily
repulsed by the British, sending the Continentals
reeling and inviting a counterattack.
A furious Washington rallied his reserve of
6,000 men and managed to turn the tide of
the battle during two hours of fierce fighting.
Washington decided against sending his exhausted
army to pursue the British, who managed to
slip away to safety in the middle of the night.
In the weeks following the battle, General
Lee was court-martialled and found guilty,
and Washington was happy to see the back of
him.
For the next three years, the British forces
turned their attention to the south.
During this period Washington would not fight
a major battle, though he was by no means
inactive.
In the summer of 1778 the French navy sailed
up the Chesapeake to join Washington, though
the cooperation between the subjects of an
absolute monarchy and the citizens of a revolutionary
republic was far from seamless, as the Americans
realised that the French were motivated foremost
by animosity against the British, rather than
support for the American cause, and once again
Washington found himself interacting with
European military officers who looked down
on Americans and rarely kept him updated on
their whereabouts.
The following summer, Washington managed to
stop Clinton from controlling the Hudson River
and cutting off New England from the rest
of the United States, but this period otherwise
proved uneventful.
By 1780, Washington’s army was low on money
and supplies, and military success seemed
impossible without the assistance of the French.
Lafayette had been in France since the beginning
of 1779 and lobbied for greater French assistance
to the American cause.
King Louis XVI answered the call by sending
an expeditionary force of 6,000 men to America
under the command of the Comte de Rochambeau
in conjunction with the fleet commanded by
the Chevalier de Ternay, who landed in Newport,
Rhode Island on the 10th of July 1780.
Meanwhile, the Continentals had suffered a
series of setbacks in the south, beginning
with the loss of the port of Charleston in
South Carolina in May, and followed by Horatio
Gates’ defeat to General Charles Cornwallis
at the Battle of Camden in South Carolina
on the 16th of August, whose dismissal by
Congress in the aftermath of the debacle removed
the final challenger to Washington’s authority
in the Continental Army.
Worse was to follow in late September, when
Washington belatedly recognised the treachery
of Benedict Arnold, the courageous Continental
Army officer who had fought with distinction
at Saratoga, but had been nursing a wounded
ego after being overlooked for promotion.
In August, Arnold had been appointed commandant
of the vital strategic fort of West Point,
but rather than strengthen his defences he
plotted to surrender it to the British, managing
to escape just in time when the plot was discovered.
By 1781, British successes in the south and
Arnold’s defection threatened Washington’s
home state of Virginia.
Governor Thomas Jefferson, whose own home
at Monticello had been occupied by Arnold’s
men, urged Washington to lead his men south
to defend his home state.
Though the American commander was anxious
about the fate of his beloved Mount Vernon
and had sent a division under Lafayette to
confront Arnold in Virginia, Washington preferred
to keep his men in New York and believed the
decisive blow against the British would fall
there, though his French allies planned an
operation in the south instead.
By mid-August, Washington abandoned his designs
on New York when he received news that a French
fleet of 29 ships under the command of Admiral
de Grasse had set sail from the West Indies
and intended to land a force of 3,500 men
on the Chesapeake in early September.
Washington had also received news from Lafayette
that Cornwallis had retreated to Yorktown,
located on the eastern tip of the Virginia
peninsula and surrounded by water on three
sides.
Washington and Rochambeau hurried south in
an effort to trap Cornwallis and force him
to surrender.
By the beginning of September de Grasse’s
fleet had arrived on the Chesapeake as planned,
overcoming limited British resistance, leaving
Cornwallis trapped between the French ships
at sea and Lafayette’s small force on land.
By the 18th of September, Washington and Rochambeau
met with the admiral to discuss plans for
the siege.
De Grasse was adamant that he would have to
return to the West Indies no later than the
1st of November, allowing little more than
a month for the operation.
When Washington and Rochambeau began to lay
siege to Yorktown on the 28th of September,
the American commander deferred to his French
counterpart, who was more experienced in siege
tactics.
Cornwallis’s army of 9,000 men was significantly
outnumbered by the 19,000 French and Americans
besieging Yorktown, and the British general
desperately pleaded for additional reinforcements
from General Clinton.
After the French engineers built two lines
of trenches, allowing allied artillery to
rain down cannonballs into Yorktown, on the
14th the allies successfully captured two
British redoubts in front of the town, and
by the 16th they were so close to the British
lines that Cornwallis attempted a last-ditch
evacuation across the York River which was
scuppered by poor weather.
On the morning of the 17th of October 1783,
Cornwallis sent Washington a message to discuss
the terms of surrender, which were signed
on the 19th.
Cornwallis’s surrender at Yorktown did not
end the war, but it persuaded the authorities
in London that it was no longer worth sustaining
the costly effort to retain the American colonies.
Upon hearing of the news of Yorktown, Lord
North is said to have exclaimed “Oh God!
It’s all over!”, and his government duly
collapsed in early 1782.
Henry Clinton was replaced as commander-in-chief
by Sir Guy Carleton, whose role was largely
reduced to organising the evacuation of British
assets from their former colonies.
Washington regarded Carleton’s peace offers
with suspicion, and still anticipated continued
hostilities.
However, aside from a handful of skirmishes
in the south over the course of 1782, the
war was over and preliminary peace terms were
signed in Paris on the 30th of November 1782,
an extraordinarily generous settlement recognising
the independence of the United States of America,
with borders stretching north to the Great
Lakes and west to the Mississippi, setting
the stage for a final peace ratified in September
1783.
Although he had been the most powerful individual
in the United States with an army at his disposal,
Washington chose to return to life as a private
citizen at Mount Vernon and relinquished his
commission on the 23rd of December 1783, following
the example of Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus,
the 5th century BC Roman general famed for
relinquishing his powers as dictator after
being summoned to defeat Rome’s enemies.
Upon returning to Mount Vernon, Washington
set out to give his estate a new lease of
life after the neglect it had suffered during
the war.
During this period Washington was courted
by anti-slavery campaigners, including Lafayette,
who proposed an experiment to educate and
free slaves who would become tenant farmers.
Washington had always believed slavery was
an economically inefficient institution, and
after the war he became morally opposed to
slavery, but he could not bear overhauling
the entire economic system on which his livelihood
as a planter depended.
Like many of his fellow planters, Washington
naively believed that the institution of slavery
would die out naturally in the future.
Despite his desire to leave public life, Washington’s
reputation meant that he could not remain
in obscurity for long.
Throughout the war he had longed for a stronger
central government that could compel the states
to supply his army, and he had not departed
from this belief.
Washington therefore welcomed an initiative
to revise the Articles of Confederation led
by his former aide Alexander Hamilton and
the Virginian politician James Madison and
was invited by the latter to head a delegation
from Virginia to a constitutional convention
in Philadelphia scheduled for May 1787.
After months of hesitation, Washington answered
the call of duty and was duly elected President
of the Constitutional Convention on the 25th
of May.
The role was a perfect fit for the non-partisan
Washington, who intervened occasionally to
broker agreement between different points
of view.
The convention was dominated by two major
questions, both relating to representation.
The more populous states such as Virginia
wanted an assembly with seats allocated according
to population, while smaller states desired
equal representation.
In mid-July a compromise was reached whereby
all states would be represented equally with
two members in the Senate, while the seats
of the House of Representatives would be based
on population.
The second compromise was over slavery – while
slaves would not have any political rights,
slaveholding states could count three-fifths
of the slave population in determining their
representation in Congress.
The convention also created an independent
executive branch from Congress, and it was
widely assumed that Washington would become
the first President.
The proceedings in Philadelphia were concluded
on the 17th of September 1787, but it was
not until July 1788 when the Constitution
was ratified, with Washington’s native Virginia
being one of the last to do so.
Washington hesitated to declare his candidacy
for the presidency, responding to fears that
he might have royal ambitions, though his
reputation as the American Cincinnatus and
his childless status helped to calm fears
of a hereditary monarchy and led admirers
to call him ‘Father of the Country.’
Thus, when the presidential election was held
in early 1789, Washington was unanimously
elected President while John Adams of Massachusetts
was elected Vice President.
After the election was certified on the 6th
of April, Washington travelled to New York,
the temporary home of the federal government,
and was inaugurated as President on the 30th
of April 1789.
When Washington took office as President,
the institutions of the federal government
were still being set up.
The Constitution had left the duties of the
President deliberately vague and it was up
to Congress and Washington to delineate their
respective powers.
Washington’s four-man cabinet was assembled
by the spring of 1790, including his former
subordinates in the army and his fellow Virginians.
Alexander Hamilton was appointed Secretary
of the Treasury, Henry Knox Secretary of War,
Thomas Jefferson Secretary of State, and Jefferson’s
cousin Edmund Randolph as Attorney General.
The Constitution did not provide for a cabinet
in the British sense, and Washington typically
worked directly with his cabinet secretaries.
In the early stages of his presidency, Washington
also relied heavily on the advice of James
Madison, the Father of the Constitution who
served as a congressman representing Virginia
in the House of Representatives.
Washington’s Vice President, John Adams,
played a minor role in his administration,
and took his duties as President of the Senate
more seriously.
Among Washington’s cabinet secretaries,
the most brilliant was Alexander Hamilton,
who laboured hard to strengthen the power
of the federal government, carrying out his
duties as tirelessly as he had done as Washington’s
chief aide during the revolutionary war.
Unlike the President, Hamilton had a grand
vision for the architecture of the federal
government and had also developed an expertise
in financial matters that Washington could
not match, effectively making him into an
unofficial prime minister.
Despite being an admirer of Washington, Jefferson
viewed Hamilton’s designs with suspicion,
believing that they would lead to a despotic
presidency, and criticised the President privately
for going along with such ideas.
The Hamilton and Jefferson rivalry reflected
the intellectual and ideological debate over
the future direction of the American government,
and while Washington allowed free debate among
his cabinet members, he was no impartial observer
and played an active role in decision-making,
controlling the agenda and requesting papers
from his cabinet secretaries for his personal
approval each day.
Washington’s leadership style was slow and
deliberative, and he consulted widely before
making decisions, a privilege that he did
not have while a general in the heat of battle.
The debate over Hamilton’s economic agenda
dominated Washington’s presidency.
In January 1790 Hamilton delivered his Report
on the Public Credit, which proposed the creation
of a national debt to be paid over time and
financed by new taxes.
Additionally, Hamilton proposed that the federal
government should assume state debts, in effect
transferring the loyalty of debtholders from
the states to the national government.
Washington shared Hamilton’s belief in a
powerful national government which could raise
funds to meet its financial obligations, and
was happy to let his Treasury Secretary work
out the details.
Any talk of taxation brought up memories of
British colonial rule, prompting Madison to
come out in opposition and break his alliance
with Hamilton and Washington, withholding
congressional support for the proposals.
The President was disappointed by the loss
of a close ally, as well as the beginnings
of the split between the northern and southern
states which would continue to define American
politics until the present day.
Washington would also prove a supporter of
Hamilton’s proposals for a national bank,
despite the arguments from Jefferson and his
fellow Virginians that such a move would be
unconstitutional.
The debate over the public debt coincided
with disagreements about the location of the
permanent capital of the United States.
Many southerners hoped to bring the capital
further to the south, and Madison favoured
a location in Virginia along the banks of
the Potomac, where both he and Washington
had property.
Naturally, the President welcomed this prospect,
but Congress was now deadlocked on both issues.
A crucial meeting between Hamilton, Jefferson,
and Madison in June 1790 saw the three men
broker a deal whereby the Virginians agreed
to drop opposition to Hamilton’s economic
programme in return for Hamilton supporting
the proposal to move to Philadelphia as a
temporary capital for ten years while a permanent
one was being built on the Potomac.
Washington was given power to choose the site,
and duly picked a location not far from Mount
Vernon, and the commissioners he had chosen
to oversee the project later decided to name
the city Washington, in the District of Columbia.
The two debates which had threatened to dissolve
the union were therefore both resolved in
Washington’s favour.
The debate over the future of the union and
the powers of the federal government easily
spilled over into foreign affairs.
Although he had fought against the British,
Washington and Hamilton realised that the
prosperity of the United States remained dependent
on trade and commerce with the former imperial
master, which recovered rapidly after the
end of the war.
Jefferson, Washington’s Secretary of State
and chief foreign policy advisor, remained
attached to France, especially after Louis
XVI’s absolute monarchy was overthrown by
the Revolution of 1789, which Jefferson witnessed
first-hand as ambassador to France shortly
before his return to the United States.
Lafayette had emerged as one of the leaders
of the revolutionary government, inspired
by the ideas of liberty which he had fought
for in America.
Washington feared that the French Revolution
may descend into mob violence, a fear that
proved prophetic in the subsequent years when
the radical Jacobin faction took over in September
1792 and executed King Louis and Queen Marie
Antoinette the following year, while Lafayette
was forced into exile.
Despairing in Hamilton and Jefferson’s rivalry,
whose supporters had coalesced into two parties,
the Federalists and Republicans respectively,
Washington sought to bring the two men together.
Despite his skill in finding common ground
across political divides at the Continental
Congress and in the Constitutional Convention,
the President struggled to do so in the face
of these two towering personalities, who had
taken to attacking each other by writing anonymous
letters in the press.
Washington intended to step down from the
presidency after one term, but was persuaded
by both men to stay on, believing that he
was the only man who could keep the country
together.
During the winter of 1792 he was re-elected
to a second term, while Adams remained in
post as Vice President, seeing off a challenge
from Jefferson.
However, the Jeffersonian Republicans had
won a clear majority in the House of Representatives,
setting the stage for strong congressional
opposition to Washington’s administration
during his second term.
Washington’s second term was dominated by
foreign policy issues arising from the war
which had broken out between Britain and France
in 1792.
While Jefferson argued that the United States
and France were still allies from the war,
Hamilton and Knox believed that the alliance
was null and void now that Louis XVI had been
overthrown and executed.
Washington hoped to remain neutral between
the two warring nations, knowing that the
United States was too weak to exert much diplomatic
or military pressure.
Following Washington’s proclamation of American
neutrality on the 22nd of April, 1793, the
French envoy Edmond-Charles Genet went to
Philadelphia in an effort to persuade the
United States to go to war against Britain.
While the Frenchman proved popular among the
American public, Washington received him coldly
as someone seeking to interfere in American
politics.
Genet made matters worse by encouraging French
privateers attacking British shipping to sail
into American ports, and threatened to go
over Washington’s head and appeal to the
American people.
These insults damaged the pro-French cause
and prompted the American cabinet to ask for
Genet’s recall, but upon learning that the
Jacobins were recalling their envoy and planned
to put him on trial, Washington granted him
asylum in the United States.
The conduct of the British during this period
also increased tensions with the United States.
In the summer of 1793 the British began to
intercept neutral ships bound for French ports,
thereby confiscating the cargo of American
ships.
The British navy’s practice of impressment,
rounding up British deserters aboard American
ships to serve in the navy, frequently caught
innocent Americans in the net.
Responding to Federalist calls for a special
envoy to be sent to Britain to negotiate a
treaty of commerce and diffuse the threat
of war, Washington dispatched John Jay, an
experienced diplomat who was serving as Chief
Justice, a choice which raised questions about
the separation of powers between the judicial
and executive branches of government.
The treaty negotiated by Jay in February 1795
did not address all of the American grievances
and tilted the economic relationship in favour
of Britain, but stopped the drift towards
war.
Washington was prepared to sign this imperfect
document but its publication in the press
provoked outrage among the Republicans.
Jefferson had left his post of Secretary of
State in 1793 and attempted to rally House
Republicans to withhold funding to implement
the treaty.
The attempt failed narrowly, but promoted
Washington to break his ties with his erstwhile
friend and advisor.
Washington’s support for the Jay Treaty
provoked a tide of Republican criticism, and
the lustre of his exploits during the revolutionary
war was no longer sufficient to shore up his
reputation in Jeffersonian circles.
Exhausted by the burdens of office and having
suffered from a series of illnesses during
his presidency, the 64-year-old Washington
announced his desire to retire from public
life after serving out his second term.
By doing so, he created a powerful precedent
of a two-term limit that would only be broken
once.
In his Farewell Address, drafted by Hamilton
and published in September 1796, the departing
president pleaded for national unity in the
face of domestic and international challenges.
Washington was succeeded by John Adams on
the 4th of March 1797, but his calls for unity
went unheeded, and the factionalism between
the Federalists and Republicans would only
become more intense.
Washington’s retirement would prove to be
short, and when war with France appeared imminent
in 1798, Washington was named as the head
of the army, but his efforts to have Alexander
Hamilton as his second-in-command in the stead
of more senior officers such as Henry Knox
was vigorously opposed by President Adams,
poisoning Washington’s relations with both
Adams and Knox.
Diplomatic overtures to France managed to
avert the tide of war and Washington returned
to Mount Vernon.
He retained an active interest in farming
matters despite his advanced age, and on the
12th of December 1799 he spent five hours
riding around his estate encountering an unexpected
snowstorm.
The exposure to the elements made him ill,
and he died on the 14th of December 1799.
A few months before his death, Washington
wrote a new will which stipulated that his
property would pass onto Martha, but upon
her death the 120 slaves he left her would
be freed.
Martha had not been consulted on the will
and was afraid that the slaves might be motivated
to kill her, and decided to free her late
husband’s slaves on the 1st of January 1801,
a little more than a year before her own death
in May 1802.
Washington’s death was met with widespread
mourning across the United States, and he
continues to be admired as one of America’s
greatest generals and presidents.
Over the course of his 67 years he had been
a key participant in some of the most important
events in world history.
Born into a colonial family of modest means,
Washington began his military career as a
headstrong officer in the British colonial
army resentful of his treatment by London.
He would end it as the man who defeated one
of the most formidable European armies in
war, securing independence for a country founded
on the principles of liberty and equality.
He would then play a key role in the establishment
and consolidation of the American political
system by presiding over the constitutional
convention and serving as the first President
of the United States.
Washington’s belief in a strong federal
government to ensure the security and prosperity
of the new nation made him an opponent of
his fellow Virginian planters, but helped
to pave the way for the United States to become
the global hegemon of the 21st century.
The universal admiration for Washington may
overlook some of his deficiencies as a soldier
and politician.
Over the course of his military career, Washington
lost more battles than he won, and his mistakes
at New York and Brandywine were responsible
for devastating defeats.
While Washington managed to keep his army
alive, he could not have dealt the victorious
blow at Yorktown without the assistance of
the French army and navy.
As a politician, Washington lacked the intellectual
vision of the likes of Hamilton and Jefferson,
and was naïve to believe that it was possible
to avoid the partisan divides that have defined
American politics ever since.
On the issue of slavery, while Washington’s
attitude later in life was far more progressive
than most of his peers, he was unwilling to
challenge the southern planters on the future
of the institution, even after breaking with
them on Hamilton’s economic programme.
Instead, he would defer the issue to future
generations of political leaders.
What do you think of George Washington?
Was he a great military figure whose inspirational
leadership enabled a ragtag army to defeat
the might of the British Empire, and a skilful
politician whose pragmatism held the union
together while the Constitution laid down
its roots?
Or was he a mediocre general and a politician
who was given the credit rightfully belonging
to his subordinates and allies both in war
and politics?
Please let us know in the comment section
and in the meantime, thank you very much for
watching.